Guide to the George Watson Cole Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Watson Cole papers
1883-1935
MS 143
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(11 boxes, 1 folio)
Manuscripts, notes, working papers, correspondence, and other papers of George Watson Cole, bibliographer and librarian. Most of the papers pertain to various bibliographic problems and topics that Cole was interested in. There is also some material relating to his work as librarian for the Henry E. Huntington Library.
Cole, George Watson, 1850-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Cole estate and the American Antiquarian Society, 1942-1944.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Manuscripts. II. Subject File.
Biographical / Historical
George Watson Cole was born at Warren, Conn., September 6, 1850. His early education was received in the public schools of his native county and at Phillips Academy, Andover, Mass. After teaching school for four years, during which time he read Law, he was admitted to the bar in 1876 and practiced law in his native county until 1885, when he abandoned law to engage in library work.
During 1885 and 1886 he compiled the printed Classified Catalogue of the Fitchburg (Mass.) Public Library. From Fitchburg he went to New York in the autumn of 1886 to become the Librarian of the Pratt Institute of Brooklyn; at the same time he attended the Library School at Columbia University, from which he was graduated in 1888. For the next three years he was connected with the Newberry Library in Chicago, which he left in January 1891 to become the Librarian of the Free Public Library of Jersey City, N.J., then being organized. In December 1895, because of ill-health, Mr. Cole resigned his position as Librarian and devoted the next three years to travel.
On his return to this country he became interested in bibliography; in December 1901, he began compilation of the extensive and valuable collection of American and English Literature and Miscellany in the Library of the late E. Dwight Church, of Brooklyn. The result of his labors was a catalogue comprising seven volumes, containing in all 3,789 pages, with 1,755 facsimiles of title pages, colophons and other interesting features of the collection.
In October 1915, Cole became Librarian of Henry E. Huntington's collection, then housed in New York. He continued to hold the position after the collection was transferred in 1920 to the present location of the Huntington Library in California.
In 1924 he became Librarian Emeritus. Thereafter he continued to publish articles and books on bibliographical and other topics. He died on October 10, 1939.
Scope and Contents
Manuscripts, notes, working papers, correspondence, and other papers of George Watson Cole, bibliographer and librarian. Most of the papers pertain to various bibliographic problems and topics that Cole was interested in. There is also some material relating to his work as librarian for the Henry E. Huntington Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Bibliography; Libraries; Literature -- History and criticism; Europe -- Description and travel; Librarians; Cole, George Watson, 1850-1939; Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery
- Manuscripts, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains many minor manuscripts of articles, essays, speeches and fiction. The two main topics are bibliography and travel. Also included are essays on temperence and The Huntington Library.
  Boxes 4 and 5 of this series contain material pertaining to G.W. Cole's edition of Ben Jonson's The Masque of the Gypsies. Included are photostatic copies of three 17th century texts that Cole employed in compiling his edition and correspondence pertaining to The Masque of the Gypsies.
  Of particular interest is Cole's juxtaposition of the three 17th century texts and Cole's subsequent version. This includes a line by line comparision and Cole's notations of variences.
  - "Account of Vacation in England, Trip Taken in 1916" (1st draft) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Bibliography, before New York State Library School, Albany, 1893 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - "American Book Collectors", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Authors Club Visit", draft and carbon of later version (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beautiful Jersey, bound, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beautiful Jersey, bound, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4a)
  - "Belgium's Famous Cities," as revised, 1927 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Biblio-Curios or Curiosities of Elizabethan Book-Making," miscellaneous draft sheets (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "A Bibliographical Catalogue," 6 sheets typed (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Bibliographical Ghosts" (appears to be a chapter or section of a larger work) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Bibliographical Ghosts" (see note above) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Bibliographical Ghosts" (see folder 8 note) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Bibliographical Jottings," revised, 1922 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Bibliographical Pitfalls: Linked Books" (draft) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Bibliographical Problems with a Few Solutions" (carbon copy) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Bibliography-A Forecast" (17 pp. typed) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Biographical Data," G.W. Cole (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Biographical Fragments," G.W. Cole (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Book Collectors with Reference to the Library of Henry Edwards Huntington" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Books, Bibliography and Bibliophiles" (Address), cancelled sheets (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cabot Map Legends in MS (photostats) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "The Cataloguing of Rare Books in the Huntington Library" (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "The Church Catalogue of British Literature and Miscellanea" (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Do You Know Your Lowndes?" (draft, carbon, with working title "William Thomas Lowndes, the English Bibliographer"), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Do You Know Your Lowndes?" (final revision), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "The Earliest Book in American Literature" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Early Library Development in New York State", 1800-1900 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Early Library Development in New York State" (notes and clippings for preceding), 1800-1900 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Elizabethan Americana" (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Evolution of the Alphabet and of the Recorded Thought" (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Facilities for Historical and Literary Research in the Huntington Library" (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Famous Printers of the 15th and 16th Centuries I: The World Prepares to Welcome the Printer", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Famous Printers of the 15th and 16th Centuries II: The Invention and Development of Printing", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Famous Printers of the 15th and 16th Centuries III: Other Master Printers", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "The First Folio of Shakespeare: A Further Word...", 1909 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "The Genealogy of the 1616 Edition of Chapman's Bussy d'Amboi s", 1919 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Historical Society of Southern California, resume of speech delivered before (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "The Huntington Family in America" (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "Henry Huntington, Book Collector" (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "Huntington Library" (Interview revised), 1922 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Huntington Library," seech at the Staff Library, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "The Huntington Library" (Speech), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Huntington Library, Report on Early English Printed Books" (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - "Huntington Library, Report of the Librarian", 1924 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Huntington Library, Report of the Librarian" (draft), 1924 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Torrington, Ct. Library. First catalogue, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 43A)
  - "Itinerary of My European Trip", 1929 May 31-July 31 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - "Libraries for Scholarly Research" (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - "Library Schools in the United States", 1923 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - "Mal de Mer" (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Masque of the Gypsies (Jonson)
    - Correpondence relative to (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - List of contents boxes 68-73 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Text A (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Text B (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Text C (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Text F (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Collation worksheet pp. 1-20 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Collation worksheet pp. 21-40 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Collation worksheet pp. 41-67 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Negative photostats of a contemporary edition (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Negative photostats of Grifford's edition, 1816 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Negative photostats of the Folio edition, 1640 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Positive photostats of the Folio edition of 1640, pp. 55-95 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Positive photostats of the Folio edition of 1640, pp. 260-263 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Negative & positive photostats mounted Folio edition, 1640 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Positive photostats of the Folio edition (metamorphosed Gypsies) (Jonson)., 1640 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Positive photostats of the Huntington Library MS edition (The Gypsies metamorphosed) (Jonson), pp. 98-212 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Negative photostats of the music (printed on pp. 15-19 etc.) (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Positive photostats of the music and other items (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Negative photostats of the ? edition (pp. 88-94) (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Publicity information (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Transcript of the MSS of Jonson's... (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Missions, notes from books containing illustrations of the California Missions (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Missions, California Missions, notes and cancelled sheets (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Missions and Mission Pictures, copy 3 and later enlarged, typed, 1935 February (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - "Missions in California," historical material (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - "Northern Germany" (24 pp.) (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - "Northern Germany," revised, 1927 July 27 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Notable Editions of the Scriptures List of Contents of Boxes 74-85 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - "Notable Editions of the Scriptures" I & II, 1931-1932 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - "Notable Editions of the Scriptures" Vol. III, 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - "Notable Editions of the Scriptures" Vol. IV, 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - "Notable Editions of the Scriptures" Vol. V, 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - "Notable Editions of the Scriptures" Vol. VI, 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - "The Photostat and Its Use in Bibliographical Work", 1921 May 26 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Poems by G.W. Cole (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - "The Portraits of Fray Junipero Serra", 1935 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - "The Preservation and Transmission of Recorded Thought", 1931 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - "Rambles in Baltic Lands" (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - "Reminiscences of the Netherlands", many bibliographied, 1931 July (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Rev. Wyllys Warner (1800-1869) Biographical and Obituary Notes (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - "Robert Browning, A Lecture before the Browning Club", 1921 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - "Samuel Daniel and Simon Waterson" (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - "Shakespeare, A Sketch" (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - "Shakespeare Checklist" (Foreign Libraries) (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - "Shakespeare Quartos with False Dates," 1st and 2nd drafts (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - "Shakespeare, Mr. William Shakespeare" 8 pp. (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - "Some American Book Collectors," List of Book Collectors (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - "Some Bibliographies of English Literature" (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - "The Special Library" (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Spenser's View of the State of Ireland, notes on (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Travel Record of George Watson Cole (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - "Treasures of Time" (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - "Uncle Ben" (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - "The Use of Alcohol in Health and Disease" (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - "What Should be Found in Bibliographies" (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - "What Should We Do With the Liquor Traffic", (1883) (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - "Why Should not a System of Phonetic Writing be Taught...," working copy (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - "William J. Fletcher's Classification...," 27 pp. (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - "William Tyndale's English Bible," carbon copy, 1927 July (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - "Woman and Literature," a speech 7 pp. (Box 8, Folder 108)
- Subject File, Series II
  This series contains biographical information relating to G.W. Cole and general correspondence. Included in this are an article about Cole by Harold D. Carew ("Toiler in the Vineyard of Books") a list of the books in G.W. Cole's private library, and a list of G.W. Cole's printed productions.
  Other material in this series includes a folder of general correspondence and a check list of Dickens' The Pickwick Papers.
  - Bacon's Elements of the Common Lawes, notes on some editions (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Cole, G. W.
    - Article about ("Toiler in the Vineyard of Books", by Harold D. Carew), 1932 October (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Article about ("Toiler in the Vineyard of Books", by H.D. Carew) working copy, 1932 October (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - hristmas Book Presented to (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Commemerative Book Presented to, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Commemerative Book Presented to, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Library of Subject Catalogue, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - List of printed productions of cancelled sheets (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - List of printed productions of cancelled sheets (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - List of printed productions of working copy (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: appreciations from various sources (typed copy), 1933 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: appreciations (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Cries of London, bibliography (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Cries of London, materials on (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Dickens' Pickwick Papers, checklist (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Different editions with same date (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Handbook of Geneology, by H. R. Stiles (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Huntington Library, Miscellaneous Material (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Masques and Play of which no Early Edition is in the Huntington Library (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Narratives of captivity among the Indians (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Note Cards (dummy folder: cards boxed separately in collection) (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Notes removed from various books (Box 10, Folder 21a)
  - Miscellaneous notes and notebooks (Box 10, Folder 21b)
  - Photos (Box 12)
  - "Stemma of Capetian Kings of France" and "Stemma of Kings of England" (neither by Cole) (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Notecards (Box 11)